hi my name is Joe Brewer and I'm an
innovation strategist I didn't just come
to this work in a direct path like I
didn't go to college and sign up for a
BS and innovation no I took a different
approach and since the work that idea
was a bit unusual a bit unorthodox I
thought you might appreciate learning
how I came to do this work see it
started out when I was an undergraduate
student Southeast Missouri State
University in Cape Girardeau and I was
interested in a lot of different things
so I started studying physics and
philosophy and I was very interested in
the Performing Arts so I studied dance
and theatre as well and pretty soon I
realized that when I was very interested
actually was the foundations of
knowledge and in explaining the deeper
patterns that unfold around us in the
world so I started digging into it an
area of research called complexity
science and I learned that there are
ways to rigorously analyze dynamic
systems to explain the patterns that are
unfolding within them as well as to see
the limitations of our ability to
understand or predict what's happening
in a complex world I started out doing
this as a philosopher and then as a
physicist and I studied it in physics
specifically because that's a place
where you can construct controllable
experiments and really in a quantifiable
way figure out what's going on in a
system and why paves the way it does now
I didn't study this to just be a
physicist I studied it because I wanted
to understand how those same patterns
could unfold in complex social systems
so when I went to graduate school in
atmospheric science at the University of
Illinois I focused on how complex
patterns form not specifically i was
looking at how cloud structures form and
how the structure of clouds can be
characterized in climate models to
better predict how energy moves through
the atmosphere but all the way as I went
along I was learning a lot of things
about the global climate system about
human civilization and about the
patterns that dominate our world so I
quickly realized that having another
physicist studying climate wasn't going
to solve the
global problems that really the bigger
challenges are in the realm of
large-scale behavior the dominant norms
and values of society and the
institutional structures that drive so
much of how we behave on a large scale
so I left the university and left my
background in the formal physical
sciences and went into a different area
I started studying the cognitive and
behavioral sciences because I wanted to
understand how human behavior works and
I wasn't just interested in this as an
academic I was interested in solving
real-world problems like climate change
or global poverty or more close to home
here in the US now broken political
system massive manipulation through the
media and a set of corrupting influences
that make democracy rather difficult to
have so as I was learning about
cognitive science studying things like
neuroscience and linguistics sociology
that I was applying my earlier training
in complex systems to look at the trends
and patterns that shape human behavior
and as I started really taking in and
learning these things in a realm of a
practitioner which means I was working
with executives and nonprofits and
government agencies as well as people
running social businesses and I was
looking at how the change process
unfolds how does my person's behavior in
one setting change as they move to
another setting and what are the
influences that shape this such as the
cultural narratives that define what it
means to be a good person or a
successful person or what are the
priorities that are given greater
salience in a society which you could
think of as the dominant values so then
the US for example we have a priority
given to individuals so we tend to have
a set of individualist values in our
culture so how would that shape human
behavior and I would have shaped the
adoption of changes that could promote
greater sustainability greater social
justice and greater while sharing of
economic prosperity so in doing all of
this work over the last several years
I've learned quite a few things about
how the change process works and I hope
this brief introduction gives you a
sense of why it is that I've come to do
what I do and how my unusual path is
brought
here